Okay, let us consider this
example from the slides.
And I'm loading it.
Yeah, I have loaded it into
my editor because I want to show some
additions and checks on this function.
And actually, if you look very carefully, you could
see that I have introduced a bug into this program,
it's not actually a correct Quicksort,
and we will see whether we can find this
bug; well, we will, because I will show you
some techniques for testing Haskell programs.
Okay, but first, let's simply start
the interpreter and load this example.
Okay, then we can call the
'sort' function on some inputs,
let's say we want to call it on this small list,
and we can see that it actually
produces the correct output.
So, somehow, the bug is not
very obvious immediately.
Okay, but let's say we want to make
sure that this is always the case.
So, let's actually maybe first preserve
this one case that we just saw here
as a repeated test case, so
that we can always run it.
Okay, so that's what you would call
a unit test in some other language,
so we simply write a 'main' definition,
which always runs the same test.
And then next time I load my file, I can
simply run this, and it will say "True".
Okay, now, this would be unit
testing, though this is not very,
somehow attractive to just have tests like that.
So, how do we instead test in Haskell?
And one reason for showing you
this now is that also Autotool
will work in the way I will present now.
So far, your submissions were
only mostly inspected by people.
So, Autotool did give some feedback,
but the correctness of your CodeWorld
tasks was checked by people looking at it.
Okay, because there is not
much automation possible there.
But for future exercise tasks, well,
those that are not inside CodeWorld, but
maybe where you have to write list
processing functions like this one,
the checks will be more about
the semantics of the functions.
And the kind of feedback you
will get will be similar to the
feedback that you can see now when
I do this here on the example,
because we use basically the same
testing framework inside Autotool.
Okay, so the first thing is, we don't want to fix
or, well, to test our
functions on some fixed inputs.
Also, because that would make it very simple
for students to cheat by simply writing
functions that work on
exactly those example inputs.
So, instead, we want to express
some more general properties
of our functions, or of your
submissions, and then check those.
Okay, and the way to do this, or one
way to do this in Haskell, is to use
a certain library, which I will
import here, it's called QuickCheck.
And this is how it is imported.
And this will from now on often appear
in the templates for your exercise tasks.
And what this allows us to do is to
write more comprehensive test suites.
In particular, ones that are not just about fixed
inputs, so we can write down general properties.
And then these properties will be tested.
Okay, for now, this uses some syntax that will
not be known to you yet, but one by one, you will
be able to do this yourself.
So, maybe you want to write also
your own test suites before actually
uploading something to Autotool, then you
don't have to rely just on our tests.
Okay, so what could such a property look like?
Well, maybe I want to express the very basic
property, namely that sorting a list that
is already sorted doesn't do any harm.
How could I do this?
How do I express a property like this?
What I really want to say is something like: I
don't want to sort some fixed list, but for example,
I want to sort any list of the form
'1..n', because I want to talk about any
sorted list, and what should be
the outcome of such a sort call?
Well, it would be that list itself.
Now, I can't write this as
a check directly, right?
So, I couldn't have written it like this because where
does the 'n' come from? The 'n' should be something,
not fixed, which would
be somehow all-quantified.
Well, the way we do this, in
'QuickCheck', is as follows.
We can say, well, let me actually
check this property for all 'n'.
And so for now, this is just some
syntax that you have to take as given.
And you will later learn what this
means in general, or how this is
to be interpreted in general.
Let me kill this buffer,
because it seems to slow down my editor for
some reason that I don't quite understand.
Okay, let's consider this
and restart the interpreter.
Load the example again, and then I can call my test
suite and it says, okay, it has passed 100 tests.
Okay, now the question is
what tests it has passed?
Or maybe this was just checked for n=1. Well,
to make sure that that is not the case,
I can, instead of 'quickCheck',
use 'verboseCheck'.
Yes, so, we're given a more verbose testing
output, because what will then happen is
that I get notified about
which inputs are checked.
And then what you see here is
where it has passed 100 tests and
what are these tests, the test cases?
Well, the 'n' has been shown to be
26, 32, -61, and many other values.
Okay, so 100 random choices for this 'n' here.
And for all of them, this property
was checked; it was always okay.
Well, this is already something,
of course, what we see here,
it's a bit stupid to check
this on negative numbers.
So, we should probably exclude this
and one way to do this is to say here,
that you want to have only
positive 'n', it's like,
basically a quantification over only the
positive natural numbers, the positive integers.
And then if we reload this, and again,
run the test suite, now it has, again,
run 100 tests, and if you check, inspect the
values here, you will see that it has only
checked for positive 'n', which is nice.
Okay, so let me again switch back to 'quickCheck',
because I don't always want to see these,
all these values.
And then we have one property,
we haven't yet found our mistake.
Okay, so we have to do something
else, maybe some more tests.
What else could we test?
Well, we could say, not only should it be the case
that if you sort the list '1..n', we get '1..n'.
But it should also be the case if we sort a
list, which is exactly in the opposite
order, that it also gives the right result.
So, on property, we could
try to check this one.
Yes, given an 'n'.
If we take the list, '1..n', reverse
it, so it’s the exact opposite,
and we sort it, we should still get '1..n'.
Okay.
And since we are already
in the process of writing more tests,
maybe let's directly check this now.
We would also run through, you have to believe
me, maybe at this point, let's also write some
additional tests.
So, for example, instead of simply saying
that we want to sort lists of '1..n', maybe
let's be more general and say how, or what
should happen if you sort an arbitrary list.
Yes, so,
I can also simply quantify
over an arbitrary list 'xs',
then, of course, it would be stupid to
expect that sorting 'xs' is equal to 'xs'.
But actually, let's check
what happens if I do this.
So, I should get a counterexample now.
Indeed, there were two tests
which passed 100 cases.
These are the first two ones, and
then there's a counterexample.
This looks somewhat strange.
Why is '[0, 0]' a
counterexample to this equation?
Well, it's the wrong equation anyway.
But also, actually, for this case, we
could have expected it actually works.
And well, maybe at this point, I
should disclose where the error is.
Namely, if I had
written it like this, then we would also have
failed but with a more meaningful counterexample.
Okay.
But that's just because the property is wrong.
Anyway, let me write down a property which should
actually be correct for the sorting function.
So, what about if I reverse
the list and then sort it?
Should I always get the same as the list?
The original list?
No, but I should always get the same
as if I had sorted the original list.
Yes, reversing a list shouldn't make a difference
if afterwards I'm anyway going to sort the list.
Let's check this property.
This also passes all the tests.
So, this is already also still correct.
Okay, so how can I find my bug?
Even though I've already
shown you what the bug is.
So, this was a property which wasn't even true.
So, let's try to find some property,
which actually discloses this error.
Well, here's something, I can think of some
property involving the 'length' function.
So, maybe it's reasonable to expect
that if I take any list, and then I
compute the length of the sorted list, this should
be the same as the length of the original list.
So, this is a property about
sorting that should be true.
Even if I don't have a specific
implementation of sorting in mind,
this is something one could expect.
So, if your task were to write a sorting
function, then our test suite could
contain this last property.
And see there is a counterexample.
Namely, if I call the 'sort' function on '[3, 3]',
there is a very strange result, which
violates this length property.
And the reason is that in the splitting here, I
introduced a bug by not splitting into '<' and
'≥', but '≤' and '≥'. Okay,
so if I fix this bug, then my
test suite runs through again, and to make
sure that we test this on some meaningful lists
now, let me, again, add the 'verboseCheck'
here, so that we can see what happened.
And then we can see that actually, the
checker has chosen quite arbitrary input lists
of varying lengths, and has confirmed
that they all satisfy this property.
Okay, and in this way, even without knowing
what the solution of the sorting function is,
one could come up with certain
tests that should be expected.
So, we specify properties of the sorting function,
and then we can use this for checking correctness.
Okay, and there are further
things I could come up with.
So, one idea would be to go through all the
list processing functions that you know,
and think about how they interact with sorting.
So, what was some other property that
we had there, or some other function?
So, we had a concatenation function.
So, the '++' operator, and
what does it operate on?
Well, it operates on two lists.
So, in order to do this, you have to
quantify what to; let's say, 'xs' and 'ys'.
And then what could be a useful property?
Well, we could say something like,
what should be the outcome if I concatenate
my two lists, and then sort them?
How should this be behaving?
Yeah, what do you think?
What should happen if I append
two lists and then sort them?
Well, that, of course, depends very
much on the contents of 'xs' and 'ys'.
But what probably can be said is that this would
be the same as if I do it the other way around.
So, what if I switch the order in
which 'xs' and 'ys' are appended,
this shouldn't make a difference if afterwards
I'm anyway going to sort the lists.
So, we could use this property to check
some further behavior of the sort function,
and it will also pass the tests, I'm sure.
Okay, in the cases where the tests didn't pass,
it was interesting that we
got small counterexamples.
So, when we tested and positively resolved,
they were both checked, our lists
of lengths 20, 25, whatever.
But when I had a property that wasn't true,
I got very small counterexamples
'[3, 3]', or '[0, 0]', or '[0, -1]'.
That's because QuickCheck not only tries to
find counterexamples, but once it has found out
that some property is not true, it is also
cleverly trying to find as small as possible
counterexamples, which would also be useful
for you when you get feedback from Autotool.
So, you will get not some arbitrary big
expression or big function call
with a big argument that is wrong.
But some small counterexample in most cases.
Okay, so let's not try to
introduce further errors.
But actually, let's try to use this test
suite now to refactor our program a bit.
That's also a good habit that once
we have some test suite in place,
we can actually manipulate our
program, and the test suite will
check that we don't make any mistakes or
hopefully don't introduce new mistakes.
So, what could I improve about
the program now that I fixed it?
Well, one thing that in an exercise
submission, I would, or the tutors
would complain about here is that we
have a common subexpression, or tail
of the list is computed twice. This
is not really a nice thing to do.
So, what would be a suggested fix here?
So, maybe we should
instead replace these two calls by something
that is computed as a local value.
So, let's say the rest of the list is this
tail, and then we twice use this name here.
Okay, let's check whether this
changed anything about the behavior.
No, it didn't, it still works.
Okay, then we have 'head' and 'tail'
here; this can be further improved.
So, we could, on the one hand, say: Well, it
makes sense to do this in one step, so to speak.
That one line, it won't change
the number of steps, but at least
somehow brings closer together these two codes.
Okay, and then actually,
we could also say, well,
taking the first element and the rest,
that's actually a case of splitting.
And in the slides about list functions I
introduced a 'splitAt' function where you can say:
You give a number, and then you
get that many elements from the
beginning of the list, and then all the rest.
So, maybe this is the nice use of splitting.
So, we would 'splitAt 1'.
Instead of saying head and tail,
you simply say, let's split the list
at position one, then we would get
the first element and the rest.
Does this work?
No, it doesn't even compile.
Why is that?
Well, basically, because splitting gives a list.
And this 'pivot' here is
supposed to be just one element.
So, what I can say is, let me
split the list at position one,
and then I get a singleton element
list and I take the 'pivot' from that.
And I get the 'rest', which can be an arbitrarily
long list and the 'rest' is used in these two places.
Okay, and then, hopefully, my test suite.
Both: The program still compiles again,
so I can actually load this module; and then I
can also run it and see the tests work again.
And just to make sure the tests
are really testing something,
of course, I can try what would happen if
I introduced another error into my program.
let's say I accidentally do the greater
and smaller combination in the wrong way.
Then I would immediately get some test failures.
So here, I get, for example, the first property
is then wrong for the input 'n' being 2.
So it's not true that "sort
["1..n"] == [1..n]" holds.
That is (in this test), 'sort [1..2]'
is not '[1..2]' with this buggy program.
Whereas in the original
version it actually is correct.
Okay, so maybe you want to play around with
these properties and the program just to get an
impression also, on your own locally, how
this kind of testing works, what kind of
bugs it can find, and also what kind
of properties you could think of
for the sorting function and
then check them in this way.
And if you want to see more
insight into what data was used,
you can always replace the 'quickCheck' by
'verboseCheck', as I did earlier in the video.